A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Chief of Staff, Records, 2006-2009
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Chief of Staff, Records 2006-2009
The Library of Virginia
44694
4.75 cu. ft. (13 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219, accession 44694 transferred on 14 January 2010.
Biographical Information
The Executive Office is a division of the Office of the Governor in the Executive Branch of Virginia state government. Members of the Executive Office include the Governor, Chief of Staff, Counselor to the Governor and their assistants. The Chief of Staff is the chief operating officer of state government, responsible for all aspects of service to citizens. The Chief oversees the Cabinet members and agency heads in the administration of state government and is also responsible for the operations of the Governor's Office.
The Chief is assisted in these responsibilities by a Deputy Chief of Staff and an Executive Assistant. The following individuals held these positions during Governor Timothy M. Kaine's administration (2006-2010): William H. Leighty, Chief of Staff (January 2006-May 2007); Wayne Turnage, Deputy Chief of Staff, (January 2006-May 2007); Margaret Houghson, Executive Assistant (2006-2007); Wayne Turnage, Chief of Staff (May 2007-January 2010); Steve Harms, Deputy Chief of Staff (2007-2010); and Kate Paris, Confidential Assistant to the Chief of Staff (2007-2010).
Scope and Content
The Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Chief of Staff, Records are housed in 13 boxes. The collection is arranged into two (2) series. Series have been designated for: I. General Files of the Chief of Staff and Deputy Chief of Staff and; II. Cabinet Meeting Journal. These records include agreements, reports, correspondence, memorandums, budget documents, agendas, handouts, and invitations. This collection documents the actions of Governor Kaine's Chief of Staffs: William Leighty (2006-2007), Wayne Turnage (2007-2010) and Deputy Chief of Staff Stephen Harmes (2007-2010).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. General Files of the Chief of Staff and Deputy Chief of Staff, 2006-2009
II. Cabinet Meeting Journal, 2006-2007
Related Material
Office of the Governor-Tim Kaine
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). This collection includes the email of William H. Leighty, Wayne Turnage, and Stephen Harms. The Library of Virginia Email Project - Governor Tim Kaine Portal provides access to the Kaine email collection and includes guides to other Kaine administration records.
The Governor Tim Kaine Administration Web Archive Collection, 2006-2010 contains archived versions of websites for the Governor's Office, his initiative sites, and the sites of his cabinet secretaries. Also included are the related sites for the First Lady (Anne Holton), as well as the Lt. Governor (Bill Bolling), and Attorney General (Bob McDonnell and William C. Mims), two statewide officials elected in the same cycle as Governor Kaine.
The Timothy M. Kaine Administration (2006-2010) Cabinet Weekly Reports Digital Collection contains the weekly reports submitted to the Governor and Chief of Staff by the Governor's Cabinet, including the Secretaries of Administration (Viola Baskerville), Agriculture and Forestry (Robert S. Bloxom), Commerce and Trade (Patrick O. Gottschalk), Commonwealth (Daniel C. LeBlanc, Jan-Mar. 2006 and Katherine K. Hanley (Mar. 2006-2010), Education (Dr. Thomas R. Morris), Finance (Jody Wagner, 2006-2008 and Richard D. Brown, 2008-2010), Health and Human Resources (Marilyn Tavenner), Natural Resources (Preston Bryant), Public Safety (John W. Marshall), Technology (Aneesh Chopra, 2006-2009 and Leonard M. Pomata, 2009-2010), and Transportation (Pierce Homer). Also included are reports by the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness (Robert Crouch), Office of Constituent Services (Marc Cheatham, 2006-2007 and Amber Amato, 2007-2010), Press Office, Policy Office and Virginia Liaison Office. Reports were submitted each Thursday and placed in a binder for the Governor that he took with him at the end of the day on Friday. A second copy of the report was made for the Chief of Staff. The level of detail varied for each cabinet officer and items of importance were highlighted by staff for the Governor. Each report contains information on legislation, Governor's initiatives/special projects, agency matters/operations, events/agency visits, audits/investigations/compliance, stakeholder issues and pending decisions. Governor Kaine wrote handwritten notes and/or marked-up some reports with post-it notes and requested follow up information from the person submitting the report. Those questions and answers are included in this series. This series provides a weekly account of the issues and policy decisions of the Kaine Administration.
The Executive Orders Digital Collection includes 110 executive orders and 9 executive directives issued by Governor Kaine.
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Governor, Records, 2005-2009. The Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Governor, Records are housed in 45 boxes. The collection is arranged into three (3) series. Series have been designated for: I. Weekly Status Reports; II. State Budget Files; and III. Briefing Binders and Reports. These records include agreements, briefing books, reports, correspondence, memorandums, budget documents, agendas, handouts, invitations, talking points, and speeches. This collection contains the weekly reports, briefing books and budgetary records of Governor Kaine (2006-2010).
Live Websites
The Virginia General Assembly's Legislative Information System contains a searchable databases for bills and resolutions from 1994 to the present and reports to the general assembly. It also includes links to the Code of Virginia, Virginia Administrative Code, Constitution of Virginia, Charters, Authorities, Compacts and Uncodified Acts.
The Virginia State Budget Portal provides information about Budget Bills, Budget Amendments, and Committee Reports related to the budget from 1996 to the present.
The Virginia Department of Planning and Budget assists the Governor's Office, General Assembly, and state agencies develop and implement the budget. The website contains information on Virginia's budget from 2000 to the present.
The Secretary of Finance's website contains monthly revenue reports (FY 2000 to the present) and presentations to the joint money committees (1999 to the present).
Contents List
- I. General Files of the Chief of Staff and Deputy Chief of Staff, 2006-2009., Extent: 4.40 cubic feet (12 boxes). (Box 1-12)
  The General Files of the Chief of Staff series is housed in 12 boxes and is arranged into three subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. William Leighty; B. Wayne Turnage; and C. Stephen Harms.
  - A. William Leighty, 2006-2007.
    This subseries is housed in 9 boxes and is divided into four sections: Cabinet Weekly Reports, Briefing Binders, General Correspondence, and Budget Files. Leighty served as Governor Kaine's Chief of Staff from January 2006 to May 2007.
    - Cabinet Weekly Reports, 2006-2007.
      The Cabinet Weekly Reports subseries is housed in 5 boxes, arranged chronologically and contains the weekly reports submitted to the Governor and Chief of Staff by the Governor's Cabinet, including the Secretaries of Administration (Viola Baskerville), Agriculture and Forestry (Robert S. Bloxom), Commerce and Trade (Patrick O. Gottschalk), Commonwealth (Daniel C. LeBlanc, Jan-Mar. 2006 and Katherine K. Hanley (Mar. 2006-2010), Education (Dr. Thomas R. Morris), Finance (Jody Wagner, 2006-2008 and Richard D. Brown, 2008-2010), Health and Human Resources (Marilyn Tavenner), Natural Resources (Preston Bryant), Public Safety (John W. Marshall), Technology (Aneesh Chopra, 2006-2009 and Leonard M. Pomata, 2009-2010), and Transportation (Pierce Homer). Also included are reports by the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness (Robert Crouch), Office of Constituent Services (Marc Cheatham, 2006-2007 and Amber Amato, 2007-2010), Press Office, Policy Office and Virginia Liaison Office. Reports were submitted each Thursday and placed in a binder for the Governor and the Chief of Staff that each took with them at the end of the day on Friday. The reports in this series are the Chief of Staff copy. The level of detail varied for each cabinet officer and items of importance were highlighted by staff for the Governor. Each report contains information on legislation, Governor's initiatives/special projects, agency matters/operations, events/agency visits, audits/investigations/compliance, stakeholder issues and pending decisions. This series provides a weekly account of the issues and policy decisions of the Kaine Administration.
      The Timothy M. Kaine Administration (2006-2010) Cabinet Weekly Reports have been digitized and are availble online.
      Notable topics and issues include: avian flu, Blue Crab disaster relief, Defense Base Closure and Realignment Commission (BRAC), Capitol Square and Capital Building renovations, Civil Rights Memorial, Dulles Corridor Rail Project, 8th and 9th Street Office Buildings, Early Childhood Education, Education for a Lifetime, eVa, Governor's Campus Security Conference, Health IT, Hurricane Evaluation and Sheltering Task Force, Land Conservation, minority procurement and SWAM (Small, Women and Minority) business, Public Safety Memorial Commission, Telework, Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA) problems, Virginia Tech shooting, and Weekly Ford Plant Reports (closure of Norfolk Assembly Plant).
      - 26 January 2006 - 9 February 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 16 February 2006 - 2 March 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 9 March 2006 - 23 March 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - 30 March 2006 - 13 April 2006 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - 20 April 2006 - 4 May 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 11 May 2006 - 18 May 2006 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 25 May 2006 - 1 June 2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - 8 June 2006 - 15 June 2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - 22 June 2006 - 13 July 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - 20 July 2006 - 27 July 2006 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 3 August 2006 - 10 August 2006 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - 17 August 2006 - 24 August 2006 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 31 August 2006 - 7 September 2006 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - 14 September 2006 - 21 September 2006 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 28 September 2006 - 5 October 2006 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - 12 October 2006 - 19 October 2006 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - 26 October 2006 - 2 November 2006 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - 9 November 2006 - 16 November 2006 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - 30 November 2006 - 7 December 2006 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 4 January 2007 - 11 January 2007 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - 18 January 2007 - 25 January 2007 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - 1 February 2007 - 8 February 2007 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - 16 February 2007 - 23 February 2007 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - 1 March 2007 - 8 March 2007 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - 15 March 2007 - 22 March 2007 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - 29 March 2007 - 5 April 2007 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - 12 April 2007 - 19 April 2007 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - 26 April 2007 - 10 May 2007 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - 17 May 2007 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Briefing Binders, 2006-2007.
      The Briefing Binders subseries is housed in 1 box and arranged chronologically. Records include: Executive Leadership Retreat of the Governor-Elect, 6 January 2006; Annual Virginia Congressional Delegation Briefing, 12 February 2007; National Governors Association Winter Meeting, 24-26 February 2007; Briefing for Congressional Delegation, 22 March 2007; and Virginia State Board of Elections briefing binder on selection of agency head, 2007. Virginia State Board of Elections briefing binder is restricted for 75 years (contains personnel records).
      - Executive Leadership Retreat of the Governor-Elect, 6 January 2006 (part one) (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Executive Leadership Retreat of the Governor-Elect, 6 January 2006 (part two) (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Briefing Documents for Congressional Delegation, 27 March 2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Annual Virginia Congressional Delegation Briefing, 12 February 2007 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - National Governors Association Winter Meeting, 24-26 February 2007 (part one) (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - National Governors Association Winter Meeting, 24-26 February 2007 (part two) (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Virginia State Board of Elections briefing binder (RESTRICTED - DO NOT SERVE) (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - General Correspondence, 2006-2007.
      The General Correspondence subseries is housed in 1 box and arranged chronologically. Subseries documents correspondence from William H. Leighty, Governor Kaine's Chief of Staff from January 2006 to May 2007. Includes letters of recommendation, thank you notes, invitations and employment requests.
      - Correspondence, February 2006 - May 2006 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, June 2006 - December 2006 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, January 2007 - May 2007 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - State Budget Files, 2006.
      The State Budget Files subseries is housed in 3 box and arranged chronologically. This subseries documents the development of Governor Kaine's 2007 budget from October to December 2006. Records include budget meeting agendas, handouts, notes, and budget requests.
      - Budget Meeting, 18 October 2006 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Budget Meeting, 24 October 2006 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Budget Meeting, 1 November 2006 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Budget Meeting, 3 November 2006 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Budget Meeting, 8 November 2006 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Budget Meeting, 9 November 2006 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Budget Meeting, 10 November 2006 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - 2007 Budget Binder, 10 November 2006 (part one) (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - 2007 Budget Binder, 10 November 2006 (part two) (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Budget Documents, 14-15 November 2006 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Budget Meeting, 19 November 2006 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Budget Documents, November 2006 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Budget Meeting, 21 November 2006 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Budget Meeting, 22 November 2006 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Budget Meeting, 26 November 2006 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Budget Meeting, 28 November 2006 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Budget Meeting, 29 November 2006 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Budget Meeting, 1 December 2006 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Budget Meeting, 2 December 2006 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Budget Documents, 15 December 2006 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - B. Wayne Turnage, 2007-2009.
    This subseries is housed in 1 box and includes correspondence, invitations, and memorandums. Turnage served as Governor Kaine's Chief of Staff from May 2007 to January 2010.
    - General Correspondence, 2007-2009 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Invitations to the Chief of Staff, 2007-2009 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Memorandums, 2007-2009 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Governor's Cabinet Retreat Briefing Book, 16 June 2007 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Computer Matching and Privacy Protection Act Agreement Between the Social Security Administration and the State of Virginia, 2009 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - NGA Awards Program for Distinguished Service to State Government, Potential Nominees for Consideration, May 2009 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - C. Stephen Harms, 2007-2009.
    This subseries is housed in 2 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by subject. Harms served as Governor Kaine's Deputy Secretary of Health and Human Resources (January 2006 to June 2007) and Deputy Chief of Staff from June 2007 to January 2010.
    - American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (ARRA), Grants and Workgroup, 2009 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Comprehensive Services Act (CSA), Custody Relinquishment, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Comprehensive Services Act (CSA) Budget Transformation/Casey Strategic Consulting Group (CSCG), 2007 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Governor's Advisory Council on Revenue Estimates (GACRE), Meeting, 5 August 2009 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Dept. of Health, Shady Grove Water, 2009 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Health Care Reform Proposals, 2007-2009 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Health Information Technology Interoperability Advisory Committee (Health IT), 2008-2009 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Housing for Mentally Disabled, 2009 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Involuntary Commitment and Guns, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Marriage Commission, Family Foundation, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Dept. of Medical Assistance (DMAS)/Multi-Agency Rx Initiative, 2009 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Dept. of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Projects, 2009 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Dept. of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services Transformation Plan, 2007-2008 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - McKinsley Contract, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Statewide Agencies Radio System (STARS), 2009 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Streamlining/Restructuring Ideas, 2007 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Telework Policy, 2008 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Tech Shooting, 2007-2009 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Western State Hospital Project, 2009 (Box 12, Folder 9)
- II. Cabinet Meeting Journal, 2006-2007., Extent: 0.35 cubic feet (1 box). (Box 13)
  The Cabinet Meeting Journal, 2006-2007 is housed in 1 box and is arranged chronologically. The Cabinet Meeting Journal was maintained by Governor Kaine's Chief of Staff, Bill Leighty, and were kept in a binder by year. The Journal contains meeting agendas and presentation handouts of a variety of topics of current interest. Typically, the handouts included in the binder are from invited presenters to Cabinet meetings. Cabinet Meeting Journals were not kept after Leighty retired in 2007.
  - January 2006-February 2006 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - March 2006-December 2006 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - January 2007-March 2007 (Box 13, Folder 3)